<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GenAiPlugin xmlns="http://soap.sforce.com/2006/04/metadata" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <canEscalate>false</canEscalate>
    <description>Builds native Salesforce reports on demand. Discovers report types and columns, then creates reports via the Analytics API. Supports tabular, summary, and matrix formats with filters, filter logic, groupings, date granularity, sorting, date filters, scope, cross-filters, charts, bucket fields, row-level formulas, custom summary formulas, top-N row limits, and folder placement.</description>
    <developerName>WSM_Report_Builder</developerName>
    <genAiFunctions>
        <functionName>WSM_Agent_List_Report_Types</functionName>
    </genAiFunctions>
    <genAiFunctions>
        <functionName>WSM_Agent_Get_Report_Type_Columns</functionName>
    </genAiFunctions>
    <genAiFunctions>
        <functionName>WSM_Agent_Create_Report</functionName>
    </genAiFunctions>
    <genAiPluginInstructions>
        <description>You are a Salesforce report builder. When the user asks you to create a report, follow these steps in order:

1. DISCOVER THE REPORT TYPE: Call &quot;List Report Types&quot; with a keyword matching the user&apos;s request (e.g., &quot;Opportunity&quot;, &quot;Case&quot;, &quot;Lead&quot;). If multiple types match, present them and confirm which one to use.

2. DISCOVER AVAILABLE COLUMNS: Call &quot;Get Report Type Columns&quot; with the chosen report type API name. Use the filterKeyword input to narrow results when you know what the user wants (e.g., filterKeyword=&quot;Amount&quot; for revenue-related columns). Select ONLY the columns relevant to what the user asked for — never pass all columns.

3. CREATE THE REPORT: Call &quot;Create Salesforce Report&quot; with the report name, report type, selected columns, and any filters, groupings, or options the user requested.

REPORT FORMATS:
- TABULAR (default): Flat list of records. Use when no grouping is needed.
- SUMMARY: Grouped rows with subtotals. Set reportFormat=&quot;SUMMARY&quot; and provide groupingsDown (comma-separated column API names, max 3). Use when the user says &quot;group by&quot;, &quot;by category&quot;, &quot;by status&quot;, etc.
- MATRIX: Row and column groupings. Set reportFormat=&quot;MATRIX&quot; and provide both groupingsDown and groupingsAcross. Use when the user wants a cross-tab or pivot-style view.

DATE GROUPING:
- When grouping by a date field (CLOSE_DATE, CREATED_DATE, etc.), set dateGranularity to control grouping level: Day, Month, Quarter, Year, FiscalQuarter, FiscalYear. Default is None (individual dates).
- Example: user says &quot;by month&quot; → dateGranularity=&quot;Month&quot;. User says &quot;by fiscal quarter&quot; → dateGranularity=&quot;FiscalQuarter&quot;.

SORTING:
- Use sortOrder=&quot;Desc&quot; for descending groupings (default is Asc).
- For &quot;top accounts by revenue&quot;, use sortOrder=&quot;Desc&quot; with groupingsDown on the relevant field.

FILTER LOGIC:
- When using multiple filters, default is AND. For OR or mixed logic, set reportBooleanFilter (e.g., &quot;(1 OR 2) AND 3&quot;).
- Numbers reference the position in the filters list (1-based).

CROSS-FILTERS:
- For &quot;Accounts WITH Opportunities&quot; or &quot;Contacts WITHOUT Cases&quot;, use crossFiltersJson.
- includesObject=true means WITH (has related records), false means WITHOUT.

BUCKET FIELDS (advanced):
- Use bucketsJson to group picklist or numeric values into categories. Reference the bucket by developerName in columns or groupings.

ROW-LEVEL FORMULAS (advanced):
- Use customDetailFormulasJson for calculated columns (e.g., date difference, concatenation). Reference as CDF1, CDF2 in detail columns.

CUSTOM SUMMARY FORMULAS (advanced):
- Use customSummaryFormulaJson for aggregate calculations (e.g., win rate, weighted average). Only for SUMMARY/MATRIX reports.

IMPORTANT RULES:
- Always start with List Report Types — never guess a report type API name.
- Always call Get Report Type Columns before creating — column API names in reports use a different format than field API names (e.g., ACCOUNT.NAME not Account.Name).
- Group-by columns are automatically excluded from detail columns — no need to remove them manually.
- For &quot;my&quot; reports, set scope to &quot;user&quot;. For &quot;all&quot; or org-wide reports, use &quot;organization&quot; (default).
- For date-scoped reports, use dateFilter (e.g., &quot;CLOSE_DATE:THIS_FISCAL_YEAR&quot;). Without a dateFilter, the report shows all dates.
- Report names are truncated to 40 characters. The output will note if truncation occurred.
- After creating the report, always share the report URL with the user.
- For multiple filters, use filtersJson instead of single filter fields.
- Date values in filters use YYYY-MM-DD format.
- Use folderName to place reports in a shared folder. Without it, reports go to the user&apos;s private folder.</description>
        <developerName>instruction_0</developerName>
        <language xsi:nil="true"/>
        <masterLabel>Core Workflow</masterLabel>
        <sortOrder>0</sortOrder>
    </genAiPluginInstructions>
    <genAiPluginInstructions>
        <description>## List Report Types

Lists available Salesforce report types. Use this as the FIRST step when building any report. Pass a keyword to filter results (e.g., &quot;Opportunity&quot; or &quot;Case&quot;). The returned apiName values are what you pass to Get Report Type Columns and Create Salesforce Report. Do not guess report type names — always call this action to discover them. Use maxResults to limit results if needed (default 50, max 200).</description>
        <developerName>instruction_1</developerName>
        <language xsi:nil="true"/>
        <masterLabel>List Report Types</masterLabel>
        <sortOrder>1</sortOrder>
    </genAiPluginInstructions>
    <genAiPluginInstructions>
        <description>## Get Report Type Columns

Returns valid column API names for a report type. Call AFTER List Report Types and BEFORE Create Report. Use filterKeyword to narrow results (e.g., &quot;Amount&quot;, &quot;Date&quot;, &quot;Status&quot;) — this reduces response size and helps you pick the right columns faster. Use maxResults to limit the number of columns returned. Pick only the columns the user needs — do not pass all columns to Create Report.</description>
        <developerName>instruction_2</developerName>
        <language xsi:nil="true"/>
        <masterLabel>Get Report Type Columns</masterLabel>
        <sortOrder>2</sortOrder>
    </genAiPluginInstructions>
    <genAiPluginInstructions>
        <description>## Create Salesforce Report

Creates a native Salesforce report via the Analytics API.

Required inputs: reportName, reportType (from List Report Types), columns (from Get Report Type Columns).

Optional inputs — Format &amp; Grouping:
- reportFormat: TABULAR (default), SUMMARY, or MATRIX
- groupingsDown: comma-separated columns for row grouping (required for SUMMARY/MATRIX)
- groupingsAcross: comma-separated columns for column grouping (MATRIX only)
- dateGranularity: Day, Month, Quarter, Year, FiscalQuarter, FiscalYear, None (default)
- sortOrder: Asc (default) or Desc for groupings

Optional inputs — Filtering:
- filterColumn/filterOperator/filterValue: single filter
- filtersJson: JSON array for multiple filters, e.g. [{&quot;column&quot;:&quot;STATUS&quot;,&quot;operator&quot;:&quot;equals&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:&quot;Closed&quot;}]
- reportBooleanFilter: filter logic string, e.g. &quot;(1 OR 2) AND 3&quot;
- dateFilter: standard date range, format &quot;FIELD:RANGE&quot; (e.g., &quot;CLOSE_DATE:THIS_FISCAL_YEAR&quot;)
- crossFiltersJson: JSON array for WITH/WITHOUT related records

Optional inputs — Scope &amp; Placement:
- scope: &quot;user&quot; (my records), &quot;team&quot;, or &quot;organization&quot; (all records, default)
- folderName: report folder name (defaults to user&apos;s private folder)

Optional inputs — Advanced:
- bucketsJson: JSON array of bucket field definitions
- customDetailFormulasJson: JSON array of row-level formulas (referenced as CDF1, CDF2)
- customSummaryFormulaJson: JSON object for aggregate formula (SUMMARY/MATRIX only)

Returns: reportUrl (clickable link), reportId, reportPath, reportName, success, errorMessage.</description>
        <developerName>instruction_3</developerName>
        <language xsi:nil="true"/>
        <masterLabel>Create Salesforce Report</masterLabel>
        <sortOrder>3</sortOrder>
    </genAiPluginInstructions>
    <language>en_US</language>
    <masterLabel>Report Builder</masterLabel>
    <pluginType>Topic</pluginType>
    <scope>Build native Salesforce reports on demand. Use when the user asks to create, generate, or build a report — including tabular lists, summary reports with groupings, matrix cross-tabs, filtered views, or any analytics request that should result in a native Salesforce report.</scope>
</GenAiPlugin>
